Guide to the Erasmus Hall Records 1325–1989 (bulk circa 1775–1975) MS 201
New-York Historical Society
Erasmus Hall records
1325–1989 (bulk circa 1775–1975)
New-York Historical Society
Erasmus Hall Academy
Erasmus Hall High School
MS 201
57 Linear feet (approximately), in 40 document boxes, 21 record cartons, 14 flat boxes, 3 oversize folders, and 1 boxed tube.
Records (known as the Archives) of Erasmus Hall Academy (1787–1896) and its successor, Erasmus Hall High School (1896–circa 1975), at 911 Flatbush Avenue, Brooklyn. The first school chartered by the Regents of the State of New York, Erasmus Hall educated, initially, the children of Dutch-speaking farmers of Flatbush, and, later, thousands of students in the Brooklyn and New York City Board of Education systems, including many future prize-winning actors, authors, artists, musicians, scientists, and sports figures. Along with trustees' minutes (1787–1896) and the school's newspaper, The Dutchman (1925–1974), the collection contains material documenting the history of Brooklyn (such as registers of electors and voters in Flatbush, 1859–1860) and papers from the early Cowenhoven, Lefferts, Lott, Martense, Vanderveer, and Zabriskie families (such as a 1797 bill of sale to Garret Martense for an enslaved woman named Peg).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. With the exception of one box (RC-19a) and three oversize folders, the bulk of this collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Board of Education of the City of New York, 1979.
Arrangement
This collection is not processed. It came to the New-York Historical Society from Erasmus Hall in two record cases (totaling 20 drawers), 39 document boxes (called "manuscript boxes"), and assorted cardboard boxes of objects, memorabilia, and framed illustrations. To ship the collection offsite, material from record case drawers has been transferred to boxes, which are numbered "RC-1," "RC-2," etc., with "RC" standing for "Record Case" and the numeral representing the drawer. In instances where a single drawer held items too large or too numerous to fit comfortably inside one box, that box has been split in multiple parts labeled "a," "b," and sometimes "c," e.g., "RC-5a" and "RC-5b." Material in document boxes remains in those containers and follows the original numbering, but with the prefix "MS": "MS-1," "MS-2," and so on.
While the collection was still housed at Erasmus, alumnus Joseph W. Halpern (class of 1972) indexed it by author, subject, and title, and indicated on catalog cards in which drawer or box to find a particular item. The current finding aid attempts to replicate Halpern's card catalog and provides a nearly verbatim transcription of his work, including some repetition of items that appear under their authors, subjects, or titles.
The container list retains Halpern's subject scheme except for one significant change: where he spelled out and alphabetized entries for the school's various anniversary celebrations—such as "Erasmus Hall High School—One Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary (1937)"—the archivist has regularized the headings and listed them chronologically, e.g., "Erasmus Hall High School—150th anniversary of charter (1937)," followed by "Erasmus Hall High School—165th anniversary of charter (1952)," etc.
Items cataloged by Halpern, but which were not located when the collection was boxed for offsite storage in 2021, are marked "[NOT PRESENT]."
Historical note
Erasmus Hall Academy, named in honor of Dutch scholar and theologian Desiderius Erasmus (1466–1536), was established in 1786 to educate the sons (and, beginning in 1803, the daughters) of the farmers of Flatbush, then an independent town of Kings County. Erasmus Hall was the first school chartered by the Board of Regents in New York State (1787), and remained a private institution for over a century. In 1894 the City of Brooklyn annexed Flatbush, and in 1896 its Board of Education took deed to Erasmus Hall. (In 1898 the City of Brooklyn became a borough of Greater New York, and the Brooklyn Board of Education was supplanted by the New York City Board of Education.) Construction of a new Erasmus Hall High School at 911 Flatbush Avenue was in four phases between 1905 and 1940, and resulted in a Collegiate Gothic complex around a courtyard that preserves the original Federal-style Academy building. Excellent for much of the twentieth century—Erasmus Hall produced such luminaries as Pulitzer Prize-winning author Bernard Malamud and singer Barbra Streisand—the school's prominence declined in the 1970s and 1980s. Centered in the heart of then crime-ridden Flatbush, Erasmus saw frequent violence and generally poor performance. It was closed in 1994 and split internally into five smaller high schools, each with a distinct academic focus and its own administration, but sharing the common lunchroom, gymnasium, library, and auditorium.
[This note draws from B. Kimberly Taylor, "Erasmus Hall High School and Academy of the Arts," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, Kenneth T. Jackson, editor, 2nd edition (New Haven: Yale University Press, 2010), 419, and the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission's designation report for Erasmus Hall High School.]
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society also holds the Harriet Oxman Papers (MS 2922). Oxman was the only female principal of Erasmus Hall High School, serving 1972–1982.
The Brooklyn Public Library's Center for Brooklyn History (formerly the Brooklyn Historical Society) holds a small collection of Erasmus Hall Academy Records (ARC.230), spanning 1787–1896.
Scope and Contents
Records (also referred to as the Archives) of Erasmus Hall Academy (1787–1896) and its successor, Erasmus Hall High School (1896–circa 1975). The collection includes the school's charter, granted by the Regents of the State of New York and signed by Governor George Clinton on November 20, 1787; trustees' meeting minutes (1787–1896); annual reports; course and library catalogs; school handbooks; school histories and student publications (notably, the newspaper, The Dutchman, 1925–1974, and yearbook, The Arch, 1929–1978); autographs of prominent alumni and public figures; numerous photographs, postcards, and other views of the student body and school campus; scrapbooks; examples of early printing and illuminated manuscripts (one dated 1325); an Albrecht Dürer engraving of Desiderius Erasmus (circa 1600); and meteorological observations taken daily at the school (1826–1869). Also present are materials documenting the history of Brooklyn and the Flatbush neighborhood, such as the minutes of the Literary and Philosophical Society of Flatbush (1836–1838); registers of electors and voters in the Town of Flatbush (1859–1860); and account books, papers, receipts, and artifacts from the early Cowenhoven, Lefferts, Lott, Vanderveer, and Zabriskie families.
Separated Materials
The following works of art have been transferred to the New-York Historical Society's museum:
•Erasmus Hall Academy, Flatbush, Brooklyn, New York, 1826. Watercolor by Charles Burton (1979.81)
•John Henry Livingston, DD (1746–1825), ca. 1810. Oil on canvas by Abraham G. D. Tuthill (1979.82)
•Jonathan Warren Kellogg (1780–1853). Oil on panel by an unidentified artist (1979.83)
•Dr. John L. Zabriskie (1831–1895), ca. 1890. Oil on linen by M. S. Jenger (1979.84)
The original item-level, alphabetical card catalog to this collection, compiled by Joseph W. Halpern (Erasmus Hall Class of '72), is stored offsite in Box RC-25. A bound photocopy is retained by the New-York Historical Society Manuscript Department, but the present finding aid provides a nearly verbatim transcription of Halpern's catalog.
Education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Meteorology -- Observations.; School management and organization -- New York (State) -- New York.; Student publications -- New York (State) -- New York.; Students -- New York (State) -- New York.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Account books.; Annual reports.; Banners.; Decorative tile.; Floor plans (orthographic projections); Glass plate negatives.; Handbooks.; Illuminated manuscripts.; Library catalogs.; Maps.; Minutes (administrative records); Newspaper clippings.; Newspapers.; Photographs.; Programs (documents).; Receipts (financial records); School yearbooks.; Scrapbooks.; Sheet music.; Signatures (names); Erasmus Hall Academy -- Archives.; Erasmus Hall High School -- Archives.; Flatbush Dutch Reformed Church (Flatbush, New York, N.Y.); Cowenhoven (Family); Lefferts (Family); Lott (Family); Martense (Family); Vanderveer (Family); Zabriskie (Family); Boughton, Willis, 1854-1942.; Campbell, William Henry, 1808-1890.; Doggett, Allen B.; Erasmus, Desiderius, -1536.; Gunnison, Walter B. (Walter Balfour), 1852-1916.; Livingston, John Henry, 1746-1825.; Low, J. Herbert (James Herbert), 1868-; Oxman, Harriet, 1927-2019
- "Archives of Erasmus Hall High School"
  - Card catalog
    - Catalogue of the Archives of Erasmus Hall High School, Compiled by Joseph W. Halpern, Class of '72 (Offsite-box RC-25)
      Scope and Contents
      Card catalog in wooden file drawer. A bound photocopy of the cards is kept in the New-York Historical Society Manuscript Department, but the present finding aid provides a nearly verbatim transcription of the item-level catalog.
  - All Souls Universalist Church
    - The Church and the Home in the Realm of Light and Air. All Souls Church and Flatbush of To-Day, 1908 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder [Flatbush of To-Day, 1908])
      The first eight pages of this history of Flatbush are devoted to All Souls Universalist Church, Ocean and Ditmas Avenues, Brooklyn, N.Y., which sponsored the publication.
  - Anthology of Student Verse
    - "Anthology of Student Verse" written by students of Erasmus Hall High School, 1931 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Anthology of Student Verse)
  - Arch [yearbook]
    "Arch," the annual yearbook of the graduating class of Erasmus Hall High School. Early issues were known as the "Senior Class Book" or "Senior Yearbook." Through 1953, separate books were published for the January and June graduating classes. Since 1954, one book has been published each year. The collection is complete except for June 1930 and 1932, which may or may not have been published.
    - Arch, 1929 Jan.–1936 Jan. (Offsite-box MS-30)
    - Arch, 1936 June–1940 June (Offsite-box MS-31)
    - Arch, 1941 Jan.–1945 June (Offsite-box MS-32)
    - Arch, 1946 Jan.–1949 Jan. (Offsite-box MS-33)
    - Arch, 1949 June–1953 June (Offsite-box MS-34)
    - Arch, 1954–1959 (Offsite-box MS-35)
    - Arch, 1960–1964 (Offsite-box MS-36)
    - Arch, 1965–1969 (Offsite-box MS-37)
    - Arch, 1970–1975 (Offsite-box MS-38)
    - Arch, 1976–1978 (Offsite-box MS-39)
  - Arch Angles
    - "Arch Angles, the 6th Term Magazine", undated (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Misc. Publications)
      One issue only, n.d.
  - Arista Society
    - [Minutes, constitution, letters], 1909 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder Arista Society)
      Hardcover notebook containing minutes of meeting of high school principals to organize "Arista" (Oct. 4, 1909), of which W. B. Gunnison was chairman; Constitution of the Arista League; memorandum providing for teacher members; and the rest of the book devoted to letters received from those students and teachers who were appointed to Arista on honorary basis.
    - Certificate and letter, 1909 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder Arista Society—framed membership certificate)
      Two framed items, under glass:
      • Certificate of election to Arista on as an Honorary Member, dated Dec. 1909; granted to William O'Donoghue, who received this honor posthumously.
      • Covering letter from W. B. Gunnison to the father of William O'Donoghue.
    - Miscellaneous documents..., 1909, 1920, 1923 (Offsite-box RC-3a, Folder Arista)
      ... including:
      • The Arista League Constitution (printed copy).
      • The Masque of Arista (Program of Arista ceremony held Jan. 12 and 13, 1920; May 3, 1923).
      • Membership certificate of Willis Boughton, Dec. 1909.
  - Bergen, Teunis G.
    - Genealogy of the Lefferts family (Albany: Munsell), 1878 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Bergen. Lefferts Genealogy)
      Presentation copy from John Lefferts to Dr. John L. Zabriskie, Sept. 28, 1878.
  - Berkowsky, Ruth Levinson (EHHS math teacher)
    - "Papyrus: The First Twenty-Five Years, 1931–1955. Published by the XYZ Club of Erasmus Hall High School Under the Guidance of Ruth Levinson Berkowsky" (Offsite-box RC-4b, Volume Papyrus: The First Twenty-Five Years)
      This bound memorial copy was given to EHHS by Mr. and Mrs. M. Gerson. It includes a foreword by Ellis Johnson (Chrmn., Math. Department), and Dr. John F. McNeill; and a eulogy by the faculty.
  - Biota
    - "Biota," published by the Biology Department of EHHS, 1959–1974 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Science Publications including Biota)
      • 1959 (Spring)
      • 1969
      • 1970
      • 1973 (2 copies)
      • 1974
  - Board of Education of the City of Brooklyn
    - Annual report of the Superintendent of Public Instruction to the Board of Education of the city of Brooklyn, 1896 (Offsite-box RC-11, Folder Annual Report... Board of Education...)
      This 243-page report contains much information about Erasmus Hall, which was transferred to the city of Brooklyn in 1896.
  - Board of Education of the City of New York
    - Journal of the Board of Education of the City of New York. New York, 1898 (Offsite-box RC-11, Folder Board of Education misc. publications)
      666 p. Minutes of the newly-formed Board of Education of Greater New York.
  - Bookplates
    - [Bookplate of Abraham Lott], 1762 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Book (1745) with bookplate of Abraham Lott)
      18th century engraved armorial bookplate of Abraham Lott. Signed on title page, "Abrm Lott junr 1762," but the bookplate may be that of the senior Abraham Lott (1684–1754). Meijers, L. Woordenschat... Amsterdam, 1745.
  - Boughton, Willis A. (EHHS teacher, 1899–1924)
    - "Papers and Letters in re the History of Erasmus Hall Academy and H.S.", undated (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Correspondence Relating to the Chronicles of Erasmus Hall (1906))
      Mr. Boughton was responsible for much of the work which went into compiling the Chronicles of Erasmus Hall (1906). A folder marked by Mr. Boughton as "Papers and Letters in re the History of Erasmus Hall Academy and H.S." can be found in: Records Case, Drawer 1, Folder marked "Correspondence Relating to Chronicles of Erasmus Hall."
    - "Willis Boughton: a biographical sketch", undated (Offsite-box RC-2, Folder Willis Boughton, teacher, EHHS, 1899–1924)
      Pages 45–46 deal with his years at Erasmus Hall. This copy inscribed to Mrs. Harriet Oxman.
    - "Battle of Brooklyn" (New York, Exposition Press), 1944 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
      A 26-page narrative poem describing the Battle of Brooklyn (better known as the Battle of Long Island).
  - Brooklyn College
    - [Correspondence and program], 1925–1926, 1955 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn College)
      • Correspondence addressed to Dr. J. Herbert Low (EHHS principal) by the University Club of Brooklyn and other organizations, enlisting his aid in the erection of an institution of higher learning in Brooklyn, to be known as Brooklyn College. Dates 1925–1926.
      • Program for dedication of Whitman Hall, Brooklyn College, Jan. 13, 1955.
  - Brooklyn Daily Eagle
    - Brooklyn Eagle and Kings County Democrat, [1841 October 26] (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Erasmus Hall Academy—Advertisements)
      Facsimile [of v.1, no. 1] issued as part of the Centennial Edition of the Eagle (1941). Includes advt. placed by Erasmus Hall Academy on p. 1.
    - Brooklyn Daily Eagle, Consolidation Supplement, 1898 January 2 (Offsite-box RC-7, Folder Brooklyn Daily Eagle special issues)
      Well-illustrated 32 p. supplement issued on the occasion of the consolidation of the five boroughs into Greater New York.
    - Brooklyn Daily Eagle, Seventieth Anniversary Number, 1911 October 26 (Offsite-box RC-7, Folder Brooklyn Daily Eagle special issues)
      Mostly history of the Eagle, but with numerous articles on Brooklyn, including a chronology of its history to 1911. A reproduction of the advertisement of Erasmus Hall from the first issue of the Eagle (1841) appears on p. 34. Mutilated: p.19–20, 23–26 missing.
    - Brooklyn Daily Eagle, Special Magazine Section, 1917 October 25 (Offsite-box RC-7, Folder Brooklyn Daily Eagle special issues)
      "Brooklyn and Long Island in the War."
    - Brooklyn Daily Eagle, 80th Anniversary Section, 1921 October 26 (Offsite-box RC-7, Folder Brooklyn Daily Eagle special issues)
      "Brooklyn To-Day": emphasis on Brooklyn as a manufacturing center. Many advertisements. (Picture of EHHS, p. 18).
    - Brooklyn Daily Eagle [NOT PRESENT], 1937 October 24 (Box [unknown])
      P. 1–2 of section G. 97th Anniversary Section of the Eagle, with reproduction of p. 1 of the first issue, Oct. 26, 1841.
      Listed as being in Drawer 7.
    - Brooklyn Eagle, supplement, 1945 December 9 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder "Staging Area—Brooklyn.")
      "Staging Area—Brooklyn." A history of Brooklyn's role in World War II. 64 p. (8 copies)
  - Brooklyn directory
    - [Spooner's Brooklyn Directory for the Year 1829] (Brooklyn, N.Y.: Alden Spooner), 1829 June (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Brooklyn Directory, 1829)
      85 p. Either lacks title page or was issued without one.
  - Brooklyn, Flatbush & Coney Island Railway Co.
    - Conductor's Cash Report, Brooklyn, Flatbush & Coney Island Railway Co., 188- (Offsite-box RC-6b, Folder Flatbush—Highways and Roads (maps))
      Blank paper, 3 ½ x 8 ½, with printed date "188_." On the reverse, in pencil: "P. W. Watkins, Genl. Ticket Agt., BF & CI Ry, Prospect Park."
      (Found in a book in the old Academy library, August, 1972)
  - Brooklyn Historical Pageant
    - [Program and correspondence], 1915, 1936 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
      • Brooklyn Historical Pageant Official Souvenir Program. May 21 and 22, 1915.
      • Brooklyn Historical Pageant, 1936—correspondence.
  - Brooklyn Life
    - Brooklyn Life, v. 56, no. 1458, 1918 February 9 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn Life—Flatbush issue, 1918)
      Special issue devoted to "Flatbush: Its Growth, Commercial Development, and Future Possibilities." Contains dozens of choice photographs of Flatbush as it appeared in 1918.
  - Brooklyn, New York—History (general)
    - "Excursion Planned for the City History Club of New York. No. VIII—Historic Brooklyn", 1905, 1909 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
      Kelley, Frank Bergen. Excursion Planned for the City History Club of New York. No. VIII—Historic Brooklyn. Copyright 1905 by the City History Club. Revised, 1909, with aid of George W. Nash, M.D.
    - Brooklyn. v. 15, no. 10, 1934 April (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
      Magazine issued on 100th anniversary of the formation of the City of Brooklyn from the Village of Brooklyn, 1834–1934. Includes Brooklyn chronology, 1609–1928.
  - Brooklyn, New York—History (1776)
    - Boughton, Willis A. "Battle of Brooklyn" (New York: Exposition Press), 1944 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
    - Dunlap, Richard W. "Nation to Join Brooklyn in Long Island Battle Celebration October 24," New York Herald Tribune, 1929 September 22 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
    - "Historic Markers Will Be Placed on Heights to Recall Battle of Long Island." Brooklyn Daily Eagle, 1919 October 20 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
      Excellent map of the battle grounds, with interesting article.
    - New York State Local History Leaflets. "Bedford Corners, Brooklyn." (Albany: University of the State of New York), 1917 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
      Tells of role of Bedford Corners (Bedford Av. and Fulton St.) in Battle of Long Island.
  - Brooklyn Public Library
    - "Brooklyn Public Library: Installation of Francis R. St. John as Chief Librarian", 1949 May 24 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Brooklyn, New York)
      This program includes an excellent chronology of the development of the Brooklyn Public Library system, 1852–1941.
  - Burr, Colonel Aaron
    - [Letter conveying Burr's legal opinion], 1797 September 28 (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Hamilton-Burr legal opinions)
      Letter dated Sept. 28, 1797, written by R. Strong to Mr. John Terhune of Gravesend, conveying a legal opinion of Burr's. "Col. Burr's opinion and my own are opposed to that of Col. Hamilton," regarding the estate of a Mr. Van Duyn.
      Accompanied by Hamilton's signed opinion (see Hamilton, Alexander).
  - Burroughs, John (1837–1921) (essayist, naturalist)
    - Autograph on calling card, 1899 May 20 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Autographs)
  - Busy B
    - Busy B, 1915–1917 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Misc. Publications)
      Holdings:
      • Vol. 2, no. 5 (Dec. 1915)
      • Vol. 4, no. 4 (Nov. 29, 1916)
      • Vol. 4, no. 5 (Dec. 1916)
      • Vol. 4, no. 6 (Jan. 17, 1917)
    - The Busy "B"; Third Rooter's Number, vol. 8 [sic?], no. 1, 1918 November 27 (Offsite-box RC-2, Folder Erasmus Hall Music and Songs)
      Early school publication has headline: THANKSGIVING VICTORY EXPECTED: Undefeated Erasmus Eleven to clash with Poly at Ebbets Fields... On p. 4, "Songs and Yells."
    - "The Last Buzz of the Busy B, Being the last issue of the Busy B.. .," vol. 8 [sic?], no. 2, 1919 January 28 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Class Day Programs)
  - Cabinet of Instruction, Literature and Amusement
    - Cabinet of Instruction, Literature and Amusement, vol. 1 (New York: Theodore Burling), 1829 (Offsite-box RC-16, Envelope Cabinet of Instruction, Literature, and Amusement)
      Contains an engraving and description of Erasmus Hall Academy in vol. I, no. 15 (Apr. 16, 1829), p. 432.
      Gift of Sidney Wein, 1097 Bedford Avenue, Brooklyn, New York.
  - Campbell, William Henry (Erasmus Hall Academy principal, 1834–1839)
    - "A Memorial of Rev. William Henry Campbell, D.D., LL.D., Late President of Rutgers College. Printed for the College", 1894 (Offsite-box RC-1, Folder Principals of Erasmus Hall Academy (Before 1896))
      109 p. Includes chapter "Erasmus Hall Principalship." Portrait inserted.
  - Catalogue of Library in Public School No. 1
    - "Catalogue of Library in Public School No. 1, Flatbush, L. I." [3 copies], 1893 October (Offsite-box RC-6a, Folder Catalogue of Library in Public School No. 1)
      This library, which was housed in the public school on the corner of Church and Bedford Avenues, was later transfered to the museum room of the Erasmus Hall High School Library.
  - Cavalcade
    - "Cavalcade," published by the Social Studies Department, vol. 1, no. 1 [3 copies], 1949 January (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Cavalcade, Commentator (history publications))
  - Chemistry
    - "Chemistry," published by the Chemistry students of Erasmus Hall H. S., vol. 1, no. 1, 1937 January (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder Science Publications including Biota)
  - Chickadee
    - "Chickadee," publication of the Audubon Club of Erasmus Hall High School, 1931–1932 (Offsite-box RC-4a, Folder EHHS—Misc. Publications)
      • Vol. 1, no. 1 (June 1931)
      • Vol. 2 (June 1932)
  - Chronicles of Erasmus Hall (1906)
    - Chronicles of Erasmus Hall, 1906 (Offsite-box RC-11, Volume Chronicles (1906))
      Published by the General Organization, Erasmus Hall High School. Brooklyn, N.Y., 1906. 229 p.
      • one clothbound copy